<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>山顶洞人日记</title>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 03:05:10 -0400</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>学术不端可怕吗？</title>
        <link>/2024/08/13/academic-integrity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2024/08/13/academic-integrity.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
It is the glistening and softly spoken lie; the amiable fallacy; the patriotic lie of the historian, the provident lie of the politician, the zealous lie of the partizan, the merciful lie of the friend, and the careless lie of each man to himself, that cast that black mystery over humanity, through which any man who pierces, we thank as we would thank one who dug a well in a desert. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; 
	―John Ruskin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/lamps_architect/page/n59/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt;The Seven Lamps of Architecture&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Ces contre‑vérités &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; ramènent les théories scientifiques au rang d’opinions que l’on peut nier sans preuves et mettre sur le même plan que des croyances issues de traditions diverses. On voit là resurgir un relativisme culturel prôné par certains courants de la sociologie et de l’anthropologie. Si la science n’était qu’une activité dont les résultats dépendent des conditions sociales et culturelles dans lesquelles elle est pratiquée, alors pourquoi ne pourrait‑on mettre ses théories sur le même plan que des opinions qui se dispensent d’être étayées par des preuves ? &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; . &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>知识只能同行评议吗？</title>
        <link>/2024/08/12/peer-review.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2024/08/12/peer-review.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Quatuor vero sunt maxima comprehendendae veritatis offendicula, &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; videlicet fragilis et indignae auctoritatis exemplum, consuetudinis diutumitas, vulgi sensus imperiti, et propriae ignorantiae occultatio cum ostentatione sapientiae apparentis. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; There are four chief obstacles in grasping truth, &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; namely, submission to faulty and unworthy authority, influence of custom, popular prejudice, and concealment of our own ignorance accompanied by an ostentatious display of our knowledge. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; 
	―Roger Bacon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/opusmajusofroger0001robe/page/4/mode/2up?view=theater&quot;&gt;&lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt;Opus majus&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:2em&quot;&gt;
“Men han har jo ikke noget på,” sagde et lille barn. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; og den ene hviskede til den anden, hvad barnet sagde. “Men han har jo ikke noget på,” råbte til sidst hele folket. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; “But he has got nothing on!” cried one little child. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; and the child’s remark was whispered from one to another. “But he has got nothing on!” cried at last the whole crowd. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; 
	―Hans Christian Andersen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.andersenstories.com/da/andersen_fortaellinger/kejserens_nye_klaeder&quot;&gt;&lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt;Kejserens nye klæder&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
The time has passed when the normally well-educated man without special preparation could understand the most advanced work in, for example, mathematics, philosophy, and physics. Advanced music, to the extent that it reflects the knowledge and originality of the informed composer, scarcely can be expected to appear more intelligible than these arts and sciences to the person whose musical education usually has been even less extensive than his background in other fields. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
It disturbs me to see accelerator physics viewed as a nationalistic, competitive race; science is too serious a matter for that. And if the lack of the right accelerator &lt;i&gt;here&lt;/i&gt; at &lt;i&gt;exactly&lt;/i&gt; the right time is really going to kill high energy physics, I must say it is better off dead, if only for the crippling lack of imagination that attitude reveals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-list&quot;&gt;
1. Savoir de quoi on parle. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
2. Tout ce qui est obscur n’est pas nécessairement profond. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
3. La science n’est pas un « text ». &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
4. Ne pas imiter les sciences exactes. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
5. Contre l’argument d’autorité. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
6. Ne pas mélanger scepticisme spécifique et scepticisme radical. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
7. L’ambiguïté utilisée comme subterfuge. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; 1.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Know what one is talking about. &lt;/i&gt; &amp;nbsp;2.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Not all that is obscure is necessarily profound.&lt;/i&gt;  &amp;nbsp;3.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Science is not a “text”.&lt;/i&gt; &amp;nbsp;4.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Do not imitate the exact sciences.&lt;/i&gt;  &amp;nbsp;5.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Be wary of argument from authority.&lt;/i&gt;  &amp;nbsp;6.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Do not mix specific skepticism and radical skepticism.&lt;/i&gt;  &amp;nbsp;7.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Ambiguity used as subterfuge.&lt;/i&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>学术圈有毒吗？</title>
        <link>/2024/08/11/toxic-culture.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2024/08/11/toxic-culture.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Madame, vous voyez la science de haut, comme une vaste tapisserie. Je la vois d’en bas, au niveau du petit point. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; J’ose donc espérer que vous me pardonnerez ma franchise, et que je resterai, Madame, votre très obéissant et très dévoué serviteur. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; Madam, you look at science from the top and see it as a vast tapestry. I look at it from the bottom and notice every single stitch. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; So I dare to hope that you will forgive my frankness, and that I will remain, Madam, your very obedient and devoted servant. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; ―Pierre-Gilles de Gennes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/petitpoint0000genn/page/7/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt;Petit point&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一封 &lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;1996&lt;/span&gt; 年由时任加州理工学院化学副教授 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Erick M. Carreira&lt;/span&gt; 写给自己实验室博士后 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Guido Koch&lt;/span&gt; 的&lt;a href=&quot;https://forbetterscience.com/2020/09/06/new-jacs-eic-erick-carreira-correct-your-work-ethic-immediately/comment-page-2/&quot;&gt;劝诫信&lt;/a&gt;——个人以为具有极高的历史档案价值：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I would like to provide for you in written form what is expected from you as a member of the research group. In addition to the usual work-day schedule, I expect all of the members of the group to work evenings and weekends. You will find that this is the norm here at Caltech. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I have noticed that you have failed to come in to lab on several weekends and more recently have failed in show up in the evenings. Moreover, in addition to such time off, you recently requested some vacation. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; I find this very annoying and disruptive to your science. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I expect you to correct your work-ethic immediately. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I receive at least one post-doctoral application each day from the US and around the world. If you are unable to meet the expected work-schedule, I am sure that l can find someone else as an appropriate replacement for this important project. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>基础科学有前途吗？</title>
        <link>/2024/05/26/basic-science.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2024/05/26/basic-science.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 一 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;1883 &lt;/span&gt;年&lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt; 8 &lt;/span&gt;月&lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt; 15 &lt;/span&gt;日&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;，Henry Augustus Rowland&lt;/span&gt; 在 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)&lt;/span&gt; 的发表了一篇题为 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Popular_Science_Monthly/Volume_24/November_1883/A_Plea_for_Pure_Science&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;“A Plea for Pure Science”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 的演讲——&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I have often been asked, which was the more important to the world, pure or applied science. To have the applications of a science, the science itself must exist. Should we stop its progress, and attend only to its applications, we should soon degenerate into a people like the Chinese, who have made no progress for generations, because they have been satisfied with the applications of science, and have never sought for reasons in what they have done. The reasons constitute pure science. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:bush&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:bush&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Basic research is performed without thought of practical ends. It results in general knowledge and an understanding of nature and its laws. This general knowledge provides the means of answering a large number of important practical problems, though it may not give a complete specific answer to any one of them. The function of applied research is to provide such complete answers. The scientist doing basic research may not be at all interested in the practical applications of his work, yet the further progress of industrial development would eventually stagnate if basic scientific research were long neglected. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
 The simplest and most effective way in which the Government can strengthen industrial research is to support basic research and to develop scientific talent.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 二 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 三 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 四 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom:2em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:bush&quot;&gt;
 	 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Vannevar Bush (1945), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/about/history/vbush1945.htm&quot;&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Science—the Endless Frontier &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Washington, D.C.: United States Government Printing Office).
&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:bush&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>我向往怎样的事业</title>
        <link>/2024/05/23/career-pursuit.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2024/05/23/career-pursuit.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
En tout cas, je n’étais peut-être pas sûr de ce qui m’intéressait réellement, mais j’étais tout à fait sur de ce qui ne m’intéressait pas. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; In any case, I might not be certain about what really interested me, but I was more than certain about what didn’t. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; ―Albert Camus, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/albertcamus-letranger-1942_20190820/page/n89/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;L’Étranger&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom:2em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 一 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Porrò autem in scribendâ morborum Historiâ, seponatur tantisper oportet quaecunque &lt;i&gt;Hypothesis Philosophica&lt;/i&gt;, quae scriptoris judicium praeocupaverit; quo facto, tum demum morborum &lt;i&gt;Phaenomena&lt;/i&gt; clara ac naturalia, quantumvis minuta, per se accuratissimè adnotentur. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; In writing the history of diseases, whatever&lt;/i&gt; philosophical hypothesis &lt;i&gt; that may preoccupy the judgment of the author should be set aside for the time being. Having done that, the clear and natural &lt;/i&gt; phenomena &lt;i&gt; of the diseases, however minute, should by themselves be most accurately noted down. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Thomas Sydenham&lt;/span&gt; 在&lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt; 1676 &lt;/span&gt;年出版的 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/BIUSante_82971x01/page/n17/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Observationes medicae&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Your god always wins. It is the longest unbeaten streak in the history of the world. Yet, J.M. Christiansen fearlessly took up arms in that battle to oppose inevitable, throwing himself in at an enemy that has never known defeat and, as sure as I’m standing here, never will. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; He and I spent our lives tilting at the very same windmills. So, why have I not lost hope like he did? Because those windmills at which we tilted were created by men to turn grindstones that transformed the Earth’s bounty into flour. From such humble beginnings grew the astonishing modern world in which we now live. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
We cannot conquer the mountains, but our railroads now run through them with ease. We cannot defeat the river, but we can bend it to our will and dam it for our own purposes.  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
We now live in a time of endless possibility. More has been learned about the treatment of the human body in the last five years than was learned in the previous five hundred. Twenty years ago, 39 was the number of years a man could expect from his life. Today, it is more than 47.  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; Eventually the train tunnels will crumble. The dams will be overrun. Our patients’ hearts will all stop their beating. But we humans can get in a few good licks in battle before we surrender. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 二 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 三 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 四 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;全片结尾处，&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;MTT&lt;/span&gt; 来到维也纳 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Grinzing&lt;/span&gt; 公墓中除了铭文 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;“GUSTAV MAHLER”&lt;/span&gt; 外再无一字一画的墓碑前，讲述了 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Mahler&lt;/span&gt; 遗愿葬于这座城郊僻静墓园的原因：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:-0.69em&quot;&gt;
He said about this place, “Those who love me will know where to find me; for anyone else, it makes no difference.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我有点好奇 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Mahler&lt;/span&gt; 的原话，一番搜查后在 &lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;1940&lt;/span&gt; 年出版的回忆录与书信集 &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/gustavmahlerderf0000fisc/page/838/mode/2up?q=%22die+mich+suchen%22&quot;&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Gustav Mahler: &lt;nobr&gt; Erinnerungen und Briefe &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 中找到了这句经 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Alma Mahler&lt;/span&gt; 转述的原文：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:-0.69em&quot;&gt;
Die mich suchen, wissen, wer ich war, und die anderen brauchen es nicht zu wissen. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; Those who come to look for me know who I was, and the rest do not need to know. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最后平静地，&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;MTT&lt;/span&gt; 用一句话结束了自己对 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Mahler&lt;/span&gt; 音乐人生的追思、也是九部 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Keeping Score&lt;/span&gt; 系列片对音乐与音乐家们的致意：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:-0.69em&quot;&gt;
To a lot of us, it makes a big difference. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom:2em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2cnOnRLBqOQ&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_laePA1RfQrAv4MytLWo7CC6LFrAkGLRC0&amp;amp;index=4&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/haitink-mahler5.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>我为何想回学术界</title>
        <link>/2024/05/19/back-to-academia.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2024/05/19/back-to-academia.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem&quot;&gt;
My only love sprung from my only hate! &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem&quot;&gt;
Too early seen unknown, and known too late! &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem&quot;&gt;
Prodigious birth of love it is to me, &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-last&quot;&gt;
That I must love a loathed enemy. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:-0.25em&quot;&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Romeo_and_Juliet_(1917)_Yale/Text/Act_I&quot;&gt; ―&lt;i&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:0.1em&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; Act I, Scene 5 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom:2.5em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不久前做出了一个并不轻松的决定——辞去了开始不到两年、体验良好的工业界职位，准备以普通博士后身份重返大学，继续基础研究；随之还将暂别读书、工作超过九年的美国新英格兰地区，独闯人文环境和生活方式迥异的西部世界。虽说选择本身几乎没有犹豫，但由此导致的人生轨迹变化毕竟不小，时而起伏的思绪提示自己有必要在这个时间节点重做一番思想上的自我审查。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我为什么要现在返回学术界？之前又为何暂时离开？以下我将尝试给出一个至少能令自己基本信服的回答。我一直认为：学业、事业的选择与其它重要的人生抉择一样，都不是标准明确的理性优化，而关键在于限定自身理性框架的&lt;strong&gt;非理性原则&lt;/strong&gt;——具体可见于一个人的价值取向、道德判断、激励模式、生活目标等等；这些观念系统又是&lt;strong&gt;个体&lt;/strong&gt;与&lt;strong&gt;环境&lt;/strong&gt;长期相互作用的结果。&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Goethe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:goethe&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:goethe&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 曾在随 &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=JRbfAAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;hl=de&amp;amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Zur Morphologie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 一同发表的一篇短文里写过一句大白话：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Der Mensch kennt nur sich selbst, insofern er die Welt kennt, die er nur in sich und sich nur in ihr gewahr wird. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; Man knows himself only in so far as he knows the world, of which he becomes aware only in himself, and he becomes aware of himself only in it. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;换言之，人的自我认知与外部体验具有很强的对偶性，所谓的「内心追求」常常不过是现实经历的投射与沉淀。这篇杂记主要不为总结职业规划的实用心得，而是试图从我最近几年的一些见闻和主观思考出发，探讨自己在短暂的工业界经历后选择回归学术的根本原因。特别地，我将回忆几个与科研表面并无关联，但强烈推动我做出决定的难忘时刻——自己仿佛应验了 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IBJGHvt7I3c&amp;amp;t=21s&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Casablanca&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 中的那句台词：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Because, my dear Ricky, I suspect that under that cynical shell you are at heart a sentimentalist. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;巧合的是，这几个特别时刻或有音乐相伴，或有颇为应景的音乐作品可供联想。我自知文字功力有限，故将这几段作品的个人最爱录音一并分享&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;（&lt;/span&gt;唱片封面链接至 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/flags/youtube.png&quot; height=&quot;12&quot; /&gt; 播放列表）&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.66em&quot;&gt;。&lt;/span&gt;愿它们能为「回归学术」这个不太轻松的话题增添一丝明亮的色彩。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 一 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;究竟什么是学术事业？我觉得这个问题有点像视觉中的多义图像 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(ambiguous image)&lt;/span&gt;，从不同角度出发可以得出迥异且互补的答案——&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/essays/rabbit-duck.png&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:0.5em&quot; /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
―Which animals are most like each other? &lt;br /&gt;
―Rabbit and duck. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一类观点认为，真正的学术研究是一种理想化的非功利活动；出色的学者通常是在受本能的探索热忱驱使，从解决难题、揭秘未知中收获乐趣与成就感，并通过创造知识、启迪世界实现人生价值。因而选择以学术为业，必要前提是能够感受并享受强烈的内心召唤。我很喜欢 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;John Ziman&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:ziman&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:ziman&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 对这种科学研究的&lt;strong&gt;纯粹主义&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(purism)&lt;/span&gt; 状态的描述，节选一小段如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Real scientific research is very like play. It is unguided, personal activity, perfectly serious for those taking part, drawing unsuspected imaginative forces from the inner being, and deeply satisfying. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; Science is not a job; it is an obsession. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;与强调内在驱动相对的，是基于现代知识体系构建原则的&lt;strong&gt;专业主义&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(professionalism)&lt;/span&gt; 视角：研究区别于创作、知识区别于作品的核心在于前者的客观性 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(objectivity)&lt;/span&gt;——有价值的学术成果必须在相对稳定、公开的评价标准下，至少得到一定规模专业群体的大致认同；故相较于纯粹的个人追求，外界的评判与约束对知识创造和学者的生涯发展实则有更本质的意义。&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Karl Popper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:popper&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:popper&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 提练过这种知识社会学 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(sociology of knowledge)&lt;/span&gt; 的观点逻辑：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
What we call ‘scientific objectivity’ is not a product of the individual scientist’s impartiality, but a product of the social or public character of scientific method; and the individual scientist’s impartiality is, so far as it exists, not the source but rather the result of this socially or institutionally organized objectivity of science. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;现实中，多数人是否坚持学术也直接取决于能否获得同行足够的认可和心仪研究机构的职位——此时学术就是一份依赖社会联系的普通工作，与其它职业并无根本区别。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最后，关于什么是学术，时下还相当流行另一种&lt;strong&gt;实用主义&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(pragmatism)&lt;/span&gt; 论点：以人才和资金为核心的现代学术研究本质是一种经济活动，它最普遍的意义既非个人追求，亦非同行认可，而在于通过资源投入产生具体可见的价值回报。这种观念貌似与传统学术精神背离，现实中却有力推动了知识创新的制度化 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(institutionalization)&lt;/span&gt; 发展，也成为了当代国家调用公共资源长期有组织地支持基础研究的理论依据。越来越多的「新时代」学者和科研机构都在尝试各种方式将经济或商业思维引入学术圈，其中一些直至把研究成果的实际影响置于工作目标的首位。于是我们思考职业路线时就有了另一条优化依据——如何让自己的知识与能力实现最大的社会经济效益；这样的选择也通常伴随着很高的个人物质回报。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;以上三种对「学术事业」的解读经常令不同背景与立场的人们争论不休，但在我看来它们更多是&lt;strong&gt;互补&lt;/strong&gt;而非互斥关系——兴趣与自由、知识客观性、广义社会价值都是一个学术领域健康发展的需要，也是个人从事学术研究不同侧面的成就感来源。然而这种必要的互补性表明——即使在最理想的环境中，学者也只能享受&lt;strong&gt;有限的自由&lt;/strong&gt;，并接受来自专业群体内部和外部的多方面约束。理解（学术）自由的有限性是我们成长为负责任的（学术）公民的开始；在这里，学术与政治产生了奇妙的呼应。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 二 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;自大学本科开始到博士毕业前夕，我一直都把学术路线作为自己未来规划的首选。这份「专一」出于几个简单的原因：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	1.&amp;nbsp; 迄今为止，高度专注的学习与思考给我带来的本能快感无法被其它任何事情替代。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	2.&amp;nbsp; 我及时发现了自己喜欢的前沿研究领域，并有幸在这一领域的世界学术中心接受最高质量的科研训练。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	3.&amp;nbsp; 我热爱知识的创造与传播；特别地，我希望能用知识服务最宽泛意义上的现代社会而非特定的组织或利益群体。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list-last&quot;&gt;
	4.&amp;nbsp; 在理想中，我希望能长期从事创造型事业，让自己漫长的人生充满惊喜与期待。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;而对于学术职业一些众所周知的弊端，比如工作强度高、竞争压力大、收入不算丰厚&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:prof&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:prof&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;等，我倒并不十分介意：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 我很享受沉浸式的工作状态，只要是在学习、研究自己感兴趣的内容；这种感觉正是我喜欢科研生活的原因之一。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 我不认为任教于顶级名校是实现学术理想的唯一途径；至少在我的领域，最重要的基础创新事实上更多源于相对宽松的学术环境和长期坚持探索的研究氛围。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list-last&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 我出生长大于一个普通中产家庭，未曾经历拮据，但也从未体验或幻想过优渥——这使得我对物质生活一向没有太多要求，也不认为经济地位能直接反映人的社会价值；大学教授那份不高不低的工资其实颇合我意。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;然而我在博士毕业后却没有直接进入博士后研究，而是选择在工业界做第一份正式工作。其中最重要的原因是：随着读博期间对当下美国学术科研系统的逐步了解，我对自己是否愿意在这套体系下长期工作产生了动摇，因为担心未来的职业境遇很可能背离自己选择学术道路的初衷。最主要的非理想因素可以大致概括如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 美国学术界繁荣的表象下存在严重的&lt;b&gt;资源分配不均&lt;/b&gt;——人才与经费过于向名校、发达地区和热门学科领域集中，使得年轻学者在教职与研究方向上的选择非常受限，不得不面对本质无益于学术多元发展的同质化 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(homogenization)&lt;/span&gt; 竞争。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 在&lt;b&gt;功利&lt;/b&gt;与&lt;b&gt;投机&lt;/b&gt;思维的冲击下，美国学术界的整体健康状况开始愈发不稳定——比如学术评价标准时常出现的混乱以及严肃学者素养的滑坡；甚至于最基本的学术道德都有在局部范围内遭遇严峻挑战。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 美国的研究型大学普遍走向&lt;b&gt;财团化&lt;/b&gt;和&lt;b&gt;官僚化&lt;/b&gt;，知识创新与教书育人作为大学的传统核心使命正在被逐渐推向边缘；教授和学者从旧概念里大学的「主人」变为新时期「学术资本主义」体制下的打工人。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;list-last&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/symbols/bullet.png&quot; width=&quot;14.2&quot; /&gt;&amp;nbsp; 近些年来，&lt;b&gt;反智&lt;/b&gt;思潮在美国社会政治光谱的保守和自由两侧同时抬头，并公开向知识和教育领域渗透；虽说目前自然科学受其直接影响还相对较小，但学术大环境的改变已经不容忽视。
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当然我有意识到：以上这些犹豫很大概率源于我在美国学术界的长期浸没，从而有机会察觉并放大了其中的缺陷——认识到真实世界的不完美未尝不是一种走向成熟的表现。但同时，长期的独立思考习惯让我无法故意忽视问题（或自我洗脑）去迎合任何貌似强大的体系。我需要更多的时间和经历来做出负责任的下一步选择。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 三 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Я верю в их святую веру. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Их вера — мужество мое. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Я делаю себе карьеру &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-last&quot;&gt;
тем, что не делаю ее!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt;
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;I believe in their sacred faith. / From their faith my courage is won. / I shall therefore pursue my career / by trying not to pursue one! &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:-0.25em&quot;&gt; ―Евгений Евтушенко, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.culture.ru/poems/26258/karera&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Карьера&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center; color:grey; font-family: Noto Sans; font-size:0.87em&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PW7dBAj9t24&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_k4btzHBaJYoVuq4x3XjIoT9omYRxhw3vw&amp;amp;index=5&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/petrenko-shostakovich13.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 四 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XiMI0c41ycM&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_n8t9nTdBqatT-J9YEFmowe91wjeksT-Ps&amp;amp;index=2&amp;amp;t=1129s&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/tilson-thomas-copland-appalachian.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ccHfDX9GChc&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_njqc-matMrey91PLHScbAOkh_NGsaKMtg&amp;amp;index=6&quot;&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;“Simple Gifts”&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 五 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
You are excluding the rest of the world that will never understand, and you have made your own world with these other people. And probably what you will never know and nobody else will ever know is whether you are kidding yourself or not—have you really made your peace with these other people, or have you made a peace because the only alternative to the peace is a kind of crack-up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Tsux27kMwjc?si=9yaMuVbJSCnjl3MN&amp;amp;t=1337s&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/gould-solitude.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0Ytqf2zXWc&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_loP8ByqcmsH-7hLj9q2cXnEcB1Y19gHo4&amp;amp;index=26&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/gould-goldberg81.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 六 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I believe that in spite of the recent triumphs of science, men haven’t changed much in the last two thousand years; and in consequence we must still try to learn from history. History is ourselves. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Kenneth Clark, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Mt-vqdgvsoo?si=qBnprXmCylsBLdIm&amp;amp;t=35&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Civilisation&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ajMWZjKovE0&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_k6SLP9aSQCU2K4tb2v73C5dRdw0zRgKtY&amp;amp;index=121&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/salonen-stravinsky-apollo.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:goethe&quot;&gt;
 	 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1823), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zeno.org/Literatur/M/Goethe,+Johann+Wolfgang/Theoretische+Schriften/Bedeutende+F%C3%B6rdernis+durch+ein+einziges+geistreiches+Wort&quot;&gt; “Bedeutende Fördernis durch ein einziges geistreiches Wort”&lt;/a&gt;, in &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Zur Morphologie&lt;/span&gt;, Band 2, Heft 1 (Stuttgart: J.G. Cotta’sche). &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:goethe&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:ziman&quot;&gt;
 	 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;John Ziman (1972), &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/puzzlesproblemse0000zima_a3q0/page/2/mode/2up&quot;&gt; “Puzzles, Problems and Enigmas”&lt;/a&gt;, in &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Puzzles, Problems and Enigmas: Occasional Pieces on the Human Aspects of Science&lt;/span&gt; (Cambridge University Press, 1981). &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:ziman&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:popper&quot;&gt;
 	 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Karl Popper (1945), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/books/edition/Knowledge/73m8mTdpsKgC?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=1&amp;amp;pg=PA63&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&quot;&gt; “The Sociology of Knowledge”&lt;/a&gt;, in &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Open Society and Its Enemies&lt;/span&gt;, Vol. 2 (London: Routledge). &lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:popper&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:prof&quot;&gt;
 	 事实上，在今天的美国，大学教授或研究机构长聘职位的收入仍然高于大部分普通职业，也要好过世界多数国家的同类学术工作；只是这份工资与真正的高收入职业相比就略显寒酸。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:prof&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
