<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>山顶洞人日记</title>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 14:48:32 -0700</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>基础科学有前途吗？</title>
        <link>/2025/04/30/basic-science.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2025/04/30/basic-science.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p style=&quot;margin-top:-0.75em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Итак, да здравствует карьера, &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
когда карьера такова, &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
как у Шекспира и Пастера, &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-last&quot;&gt;
Гомера и Толстого &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; Льва! &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Я верю в их святую веру. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Их вера — мужество мое. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Я делаю себе карьеру &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-last&quot;&gt;
тем, что не делаю ее!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt;
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;So, long live a career, / when the career is like / that of Pasteur or Shakespeare, / Newton or Leo Tolstoy! / &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; / I believe in their sacred faith. / From their faith my courage is won. / I shall pursue my own career / by not pursuing one! &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Евгений Евтушенко, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.culture.ru/poems/26258/karera&quot;&gt; “Карьера” &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom:2em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 一 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Il n’y a pas longtemps que l’on agitait dans une compagnie célèbre cette question usée et frivole, quel était le plus grand homme, de César, d’Alexandre, de Tamerlan, ou de Cromwell. Quelqu’un répondit que c’était sans contredit Isaac Newton. Cet homme avait raison &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; C’est à celui qui domine sur les esprits par la force de la vérité, non à ceux qui font des esclaves par violence, c’est à celui qui connaît l’univers, non à ceux qui le défigurent, que nous devons nos respects. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt;
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;It has not been long since the trite and trivial question was agitated in a celebrated group: who was the greatest man, Caesar or Alexander, Tamerlane or Cromwell?  Someone replied that it must undoubtedly be Isaac Newton. This man was right &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; It is the one dominating our minds by the power of truth, not the one ensalving people by violence, the one knowing the universe, not the one distorting it, who owes our reverence. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Voltaire, &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Page%3AVoltaire_-_%C5%92uvres_compl%C3%A8tes_Garnier_tome21.djvu/206&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Lettres philosophiques&lt;/i&gt; : XII &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
The outgoing century has witnessed a blossoming of science and technology in the world. Relativity, quantum mechanics, molecular biology, and information theory all arose in the 20th century, which is a testimony to the strength of the scientific method in the continual advancement of knowledge. These scientific breakthroughs form the foundation on which modern civilization builds, and they promise a future replete with material prosperity and intellectual enrichment worldwide. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt;  
―Jiang Zemin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.288.5475.2317&quot;&gt; &lt;nobr&gt;“Science in China”&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Basic research is performed without thought of practical ends. It results in general knowledge and an understanding of nature and its laws. This general knowledge provides the means of answering a large number of important practical problems, though it may not give a complete specific answer to any one of them. The function of applied research is to provide such complete answers. The scientist doing basic research may not be at all interested in the practical applications of his work, yet the further progress of industrial development would eventually stagnate if basic scientific research were long neglected. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
 The simplest and most effective way in which the Government can strengthen industrial research is to support basic research and to develop scientific talent.  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt;  
―Vannevar Bush, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nsf-gov-resources.nsf.gov/2023-04/EndlessFrontier75th_w.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt; Science—The Endless Frontier &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 二 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
The ability to reduce everything to simple fundamental laws does not imply the ability to start from those laws and reconstruct the universe. In fact, the more the elementary particle physicists tell us about the nature of the fundamental laws, the less relevance they seem to have to the very real problems of the rest of science, much less to those of society. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Philip W. Anderson, &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.177.4047.393&quot;&gt; “More Is Different” &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Physical science, which aims not only at devising fascinating new
experiments, but at obtaining a rational understanding of the results
of observations, incurs at present, so I believe, the grave danger of
getting severed from its historical background. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; Along with this disregard for historical linkage there is a tendency to forget that all science is bound up with human culture in general, and that scientific findings, even those which at the moment appear the most advanced and esoteric and difficult to grasp, are meaningless outside their cultural context. A theoretical science, &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; where the initiated continue musing to each other in terms that are, at best, understood by a small group of close fellow travellers, will necessarily be cut off from the rest of cultural mankind; in the long run it is bound to atrophy and ossify, however virulently esoteric chat may continue within its joyfully isolated groups of expert. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Erwin Schrödinger, &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.informationphilosopher.com/solutions/scientists/schrodinger/Quantum_Jumps_I.pdf&quot;&gt; “Are There Quantum Jumps?” &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 三 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 四 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
The calculus of values, if it is ever formulated, will probably have little in common with the calculus of science. Nevertheless the atmosphere of scientific research—the disinterested curiosity, controlled imagination, and passion for impersonal tests—is by no means unique. It may, and often does, produce a definite influence in those fields from which scientific technique is barred. That influence, the man of science likes to believe, is generally beneficial. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Edwin Hubble, &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.210893/page/n19/mode/2up&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;The Realm of the Nebulæ&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Quant au beau absolu, si ce n’est celui qui, dans tous les temps, dans tous les lieux et par tous les hommes, serait reconnu pour beau, je ne sais en quoi il consiste. Or, ce beau-là n’existe pas. Je crois seulement qu’il y a des beautés d’art dont le sentiment devenu inhérent à certaines civilisations durera, grâce à quelques hommes, autant que ces civilisations elles-mêmes. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt;
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;As for absolute beauty, unless it would be recognized as beautiful at all times, in all places, and by all people, I do not know what it consists of. And yet this kind of beauty does not exist. I only believe that there exist artistic beauties of which the appreciation, having become inherent in certain civilizations, will last, thanks to some people, as long as those civilizations themselves.
 &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Hector Berlioz, &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Les_Soir%C3%A9es_de_l%E2%80%99orchestre&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Les Soirées de l’orchestre&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>我为何返回学术界</title>
        <link>/2025/04/26/back-to-academia.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2025/04/26/back-to-academia.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p style=&quot;margin-top:-0.75em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
My only love sprung from my only hate! &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Too early seen unknown, and known too late! &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
Prodigious birth of love it is to me, &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-last&quot;&gt;
That I must love a loathed enemy. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:-0.5em&quot;&gt;  
―&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Page%3ARomeo_and_Juliet_(1917)_Yale.djvu/41&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Romeo and Juliet&lt;/i&gt;, 1.5.142–145 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-bottom:2em&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;去年夏天做出了个不算轻松的决定——辞去了开始不到两年、体验良好的工业界职位，以普通博士后身份重返大学，继续基础研究；随之还离开了读书、工作超过九年的美国东北（新英格兰）地区，独闯人文环境和生活方式迥异的西部世界。自从在新的学校与城市安顿下来，一晃已有大半年；最近翻出了搬家前存下的几篇博客草稿，打算趁夜深人静时慢慢写完，且作人生新阶段的一点自我记录。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;坦白说，作为一个惯于严谨乃至多虑的人，我很难用三言两语概括自己从暂别到回归学术界前后的完整心路历程；其中的一些具体话题，例如两种职业路线的对比借鉴，我计划用两篇后续博文单独探讨——标题暂定为&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;「基础科学有前途吗」&lt;/a&gt;和&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;「我从工业界学到了什么」&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;。&lt;/span&gt;但在这些实际考量外，驱动我做出这两次选择的还有相当多的机缘巧合，乃至超出理性的价值判断；特别是从大学校园的暂时离开使我有更多机会质问自己一些过去无意或有意回避的「大问题」——我为什么要做学术？我想做怎样的学术？我向往怎样的生活？如何理解学术事业对于个人和社会的长期意义？等等。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;最后，我觉得自己暂时找到了答案，尽管已不再能记清当初的全部问题。以下是我的一些回忆片段——谨以此为正在或曾经面对类似选择的同路人提供一份真实的样本。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 一 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;从大学本科伊始到博士毕业前，我一直都把学术路线&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:science&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:science&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;作为自己未来规划的绝对首选，以至于期间几乎从未认真考虑过其它职业选项。最简单直接的原因是：&lt;strong&gt;回顾整个学生时代，高度专注的学习与思考给我带来的本能快感无法被任何其它事情取代&lt;/strong&gt;。在教育经历方面，客观地说我也比较顺利：先后在中国和美国最顶尖的大学读书，及时发现了喜欢的前沿研究领域，并在这一领域的世界学术中心接受科研训练，做出了一点质量还不错的原创工作；更重要的是，我有幸能在正确的引导和健康的环境中度过了读博的全过程，被身边不少小伙伴评价为拥有博士生中少见的积极心态。于是，毕业后继续深耕、先经过博士后研究再竞争大学或科研机构的教职理应是我最自然的轨迹。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在当下的美国——尤其是社会风貌疲敝、矛盾激化的后疫情时代&lt;span style=&quot;margin-right:-0.33em&quot;&gt;，&lt;/span&gt;「学术劝退」已然成为扩散于学生和年轻学者中间的一股很有说服力的潮流。具体来说，十分有限的教职岗位导致学术人才的极度内卷；不稳定的经费支持时常为科学家制造职业危机和精神焦虑；与工业界、金融以及专业服务行业 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(professional services)&lt;/span&gt; 显著的收入差距令许多人怀疑科研工作的价值；各种物质、时间与心理压力也对不少学者的个人与家庭生活造成了可见的负面影响。因此从理智上讲，除了极少数的学术明星、少数商业化前景明朗的研究方向、特定职业学院 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(professional schools)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:professional&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:professional&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 的教职路线和实在没有其它选择的特殊案例，多数博士生在获得学位后转做一份自己喜欢且稳定的非学术工作都是现实收益更高的合理选项。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一直以来，我对上述「劝退理论」总体是认同的——因为它的核心论据基本都是客观事实。不过，我在读博期间却完全没有想过去践行这套理论——除了学习与研究乐在其中，我还认为自身的某些特质可有助于「豁免」以学术为业的一部分劝退点：比如，长期的低物质欲望和简单生活模式使我对普通教职的薪资水准颇为接纳，反而很少羡慕高收入行业；再比如，我很乐于探索未知世界，原则上不排斥在不同的城市或国家间穿梭辗转，因而也没有很介意学术生涯前期的各种不确定性。总之，天真的乐观心态使我倾向于暂时搁置关于未来的纠结而专注于当下最享受的事：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
— Qu’est-ce qu’optimisme ? disait Cacambo. — Hélas ! dit Candide, c’est la rage de soutenir que tout est bien quand on est mal. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt;
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt;“What is optimism?” said Cacambo. “Alas!” said Candide, “it is the obstinacy of insisting that everything is good when it is bad.” &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; 
―Voltaire, &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikisource.org/wiki/Page%3AVoltaire_-_%C5%92uvres_compl%C3%A8tes_Garnier_tome21.djvu/206&quot;&gt; &lt;i&gt;Candide&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 二 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;然而，我却在博士毕业年的求职季末带着歉意放弃了所有已经通过面试的博士后职位，接受了最初出于好奇申请的唯一一份工业界工作——突然的转向让不少了解我的人（包括导师、同事、好友在内）都颇感意外。我当时如此选择大致有以下几方面原因：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;首先是&lt;strong&gt;研究领域的演化趋势&lt;/strong&gt;。我的博士周期恰逢超导量子电路 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(superconducting quantum circuits)&lt;/span&gt; 的实验研究开始得到广泛关注并迅速扩展的阶段；到了毕业前夕，领域的整体面貌已和我与之初遇时大为不同：核心实验方法基本成熟和标准化，科研风格逐渐由基础探索转向目标导向的工程思路；工业界实验室借助资源优势占据了规模化实验的大部分前沿；小型的学术团队虽也能在许多具体问题上有所突破，但试图像往日一样对领域产生根本方向性影响的可能性日益减小。本科和博士阶段的经历已让我基本明确：偏重工程化思维的科研模式并非我真正的兴趣所在；相反，我更希望能在一个相对灵活自由、基础创新空间更大（即便并非时下大热点）的开放式领域中开启日后的独立学术生涯。于是我在思考下一步的方向时，首先排除了在相同方向做博士后的选项。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
En tout cas, je n’étais peut-être pas sûr de ce qui m’intéressait réellement, mais j’étais tout à fait sur de ce qui ne m’intéressait pas. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; In any case, I might not be certain about what really interested me, but I was more than certain about what didn’t. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt; ―Albert Camus, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/albertcamus-letranger-1942_20190820/page/n89/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;L’Étranger&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;经过筛选，我将博士后申请的重点聚焦在了&lt;strong&gt;超导量子技术&lt;/strong&gt;与&lt;strong&gt;基础实验物理&lt;/strong&gt;的交叉；但是这一类实验室不仅数量很少，方法与成果最新颖的还多位于美国之外。这一度很令我兴奋——彼时的我仿佛正在经历和美国教育体制与社会文化的「七年之痒」&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;，&lt;/span&gt;对这片土地的综合好感处于自本科首次交换留学以来的最低谷；与此同时，博士期间赴欧洲访问、旅行的美好回忆和与欧洲同行们愉快的交流体验使我很乐意在大西洋对岸度过无论长短的下一段时光，满心期待着收获学术与文化的双重新体验。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7iHngvUbhoA&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_nDC9hFMD9GBz6QaB9fndn_r_tX8ezVqEU&amp;amp;index=1&amp;amp;t=2s&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/slatkin-gershwin.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
点击唱片封面转至播放链接（下同） &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不巧的是，我的毕业时间恰逢中国公民国际旅行格外受限的一年，对于暂居美国但没有长期身份的留学生尤其如此。我先是以完全远程的方式通过了几个欧洲实验室的博士后面试，随后在准备申请签证和规划行程的过程中发现了各种夏天横跨大西洋的具体程序困难。在现实的阻碍下，我不得不暂时搁置了前往欧洲的计划。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;接下来在美国做什么呢？相较于立刻开始一段未必非常符合自己兴趣与长期规划的博士后研究，我突然想到可以暂时换一个不同的环境，利用毕业后可以自由选择（专业相关）工作的时间窗口收集一点在学术界内不易获得的职业经历。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 三 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;于是我向北移居波士顿，加入了一家总部位于瑞士的小型跨国公司。至于第一家面试就决定签约的原因，除了与我的专业知识高度匹配，更重要的是一种「气质相投」&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;：&lt;/span&gt;我所在的美国团队以及日常高频合作的欧洲同事（包括公司创始人）无论当前是否担任技术岗位，多数都有硬核的博士学位和丰富的科研经历；公司上下随处呈现出「学者创业」的严谨作风和对知识细节的尊重；几轮面试中，我与各位来自量子物理研究背景的前辈们发生了不少有趣的碰撞讨论；在面试后的交流时间里，他们都真诚分享了当年在学术界与工业界之间的选择经历以及对我一些非常客观中肯的建议。多年沉浸学术圈所获得的一项基本技能是&lt;strong&gt;准确识别负责任的优秀同行&lt;/strong&gt;——于是，无意间发现同类的欣喜让我果断决定成为他们中的一员。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;新工作非常吸引我的另一点是广泛的&lt;strong&gt;对外交流&lt;/strong&gt;机会——因为产品与服务在领域内颇有影响，公司与众多大学、国家实验室和工业界实验室建立了业务往来与合作关系；这可以使我走出过去熟悉的小圈子，借工作之便接触学术界和科研生态系统的多个层面，观察、聆听不同研究方向、机构、职位、经历的同行们真实的状态与想法&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:anthropology&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:anthropology&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
I am a camera with its shutter open, quite passive, recording, not thinking. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; Some day, all this will have to be developed, carefully printed, fixed. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt;  
―Christopher Isherwood, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/goodbyetoberlin0000unse_n7l0/mode/2up&quot;&gt; &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt; Goodbye to Berlin &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;由于临近毕业才开始考虑工业界职位，之前未对此做任何具体的技能或思想准备，我曾一度为自己能否适应「上班族」的角色而略感忐忑。幸运的是，我的这次转型一切顺利：很快熟悉了新的身份与职责；凭借对专业前沿的掌握参与了多个重要而有趣的项目；在同事间获得了甚至有些超出自己意料的积极反馈。一段时间下来，我开始越来越喜欢这份最初只是打算作为过渡的「社会实践」工作，并逐渐切身体会到工业界相较于学术界的各种优势&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:industry&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:industry&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;，包括但不限于：灵活合理的资源调配，科学先进的管理模式，高效透明的合作、沟通、反馈机制，简单和谐的人际关系，还有对团队成员个体发展的关注与尊重等等。&lt;strong&gt;以上感受在工作中接触学术界同行时尤其明显。&lt;/strong&gt;与此同时，日常很少有从前实验室科研的疲惫感，身心状态变得更好，以至于自发的学习欲望都变得更强；有时觉得自己仿佛又找回了初遇科研时的少年感，憧憬着在更大的科学世界里走出一条独特的职业道路。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;此外，工业界工作使我的生活质量显著提高。这其中最不重要的因素是收入——虽说工资比博士津贴高出不少，可我仍基本保留着学生时代的消费习惯&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rent&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rent&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;。真正对我有影响的是&lt;strong&gt;自由可支配时间&lt;/strong&gt;的增加——公司严格执行欧洲式的工作—生活分离理念，我可以在非工作时间尽情不务正业而不会产生愧疚感：比如练厨艺、学外语、读闲书、探索人文艺术；可以音乐会后与朋友们聚在咖啡或奶茶店里谈天说地；可以晚上一个人在博物馆里闲逛、听音乐、放飞思绪&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mfa&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mfa&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;；可以随时去纽约过周末——以上若在过去几乎不可想象。另外，我学会了规律休假并充分利用假期时间，一个人坐基础经济舱探访了许多想去的美国城市，慢慢再次喜欢上这个熟悉又陌生的国家。各种美好或有趣的经历使我逐渐认识到&lt;strong&gt;生活可以有独立于事业之外的值得追求的意义&lt;/strong&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;总结一下上班初体验——有点乐不思蜀。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 四 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在工作、生活的间隙，我也没有忘记当初设想中对我所在的广义领域做&lt;strong&gt;科技社会观察&lt;/strong&gt;的任务。一段时间下来，有幸在工作往来和会议活动中新结识了许多优秀的同行们，访问了不少曾经作为学生鲜有机会进入的实验室，总体感受是：在近些年的社会关注和资源倾注下，量子技术 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(quantum technology)&lt;/span&gt; 和与之关联的科研方向总体还算欣欣向荣——高水平研究成果的井喷、前沿知识的快速更新与扩散、高度的国际化与合作性、学术界与工业界的积极联动&lt;span style=&quot;margin-right:-0.5em&quot;&gt;、&lt;/span&gt;（相对于大多数基础学科）高效的人才吸纳与培养 &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; 有时会令人感慨这也许是当今文明停滞、智识封闭的逆全球化趋势下为数不多令人欣喜的局部潮流。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;但是，在表面蓬勃发展的领域中也能见到很多令人惋惜或无奈的事与人——比如因缺乏指导在黑暗中摸索的学生、为节省经费用尽方法的导师、勾心斗角的实验室同事、外行指挥内行的团队领导、能力出众却晋升无望的打工人、激情洋溢但不知所云的「布道士」&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;、&lt;/span&gt;自觉机智敏锐实则随波逐流的「淘金者」&lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; 当然，这类反面案例无论在学界还是业界一向都不罕见，我以前在学生时代也偶有听闻，但当时全然不会觉得故事中的主人公和自己有任何现实关联；可自从毕业后的某个时间起，我开始意识到这或许才是学术与科技圈更真实、更普遍的状态——正如物理系统宏观尺度的有序与微观尺度的涨落 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(fluctuation)&lt;/span&gt; 可以共存，科学发展的整体趋势也绝不等同于其中参与者的个体命运。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
Madame, vous voyez la science de haut, comme une vaste tapisserie. Je la vois d’en bas, au niveau du petit point. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; J’ose donc espérer que vous me pardonnerez ma franchise, et que je resterai, Madame, votre très obéissant et très dévoué serviteur. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;quote-transl&quot;&gt; 
Transl.&amp;nbsp; &lt;i&gt; Madam, you look at science from the top and see it as a vast tapestry. I look at it from the bottom and notice every single stitch. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; So I dare to hope that you will forgive my frankness, and that I will remain, Madam, your very obedient and devoted servant. &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt; ―Pierre-Gilles de Gennes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/petitpoint0000genn/page/7/mode/2up&quot;&gt;&lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt;Petit point&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不在学术界的日子里，我对科研行业和科技产业的认知变得更加立体，也对「科技进步」的宏大叙事愈发谨慎。在我心目中，学术事业慢慢不再自带曾经的崇高光环——它与世间的千百种职业一样受制于&lt;strong&gt;现实的社会规则&lt;/strong&gt;。比如，许多成功的学者生涯所依靠的除了智慧与勤奋，常常还有背景、机遇、资源、营销、政治 &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; 以至于有时难以分辨哪些才是其中的真正关键。另外，在现代学术体系中，科研或「知识生产」事实上已经演化成为与教育或「知识传播」相对独立的行业或产业；与各种「科学无边界」的口号相反，&lt;strong&gt;现实中多数科学家所直接服务的往往是特定的局部利益&lt;/strong&gt;，包括但不限于资助方（比如政府或企业）的战略规划、学术机构的运营收入&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:overhead&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:overhead&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;、应用转化的商业价值、研究团队的关注度和影响力、学者的个人职业前景等等。特别地，&lt;strong&gt;商业资本&lt;/strong&gt;对学术前沿的定义和推动常常起到重要乃至决定性的作用——这其实在半个世纪乃至更早之前就已是不容忽视的事实，但它从未像在今天的美国这般明显：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
The course of technology and of science is dictated by capitalist enterprise. By influencing the appointments of university professors, by subsidizing certain types of work, by making it clear that scientists will have a hard time finding a job unless they specialize in the directions industry prescribes, capitalism keeps a firm control over scientific programs. If it seemingly allows a certain amount of “free” research, that is part of a policy of “repressive tolerance.” That pseudo-freedom serves to weaken the spiritual freedom rather than to strengthen it.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:casimir&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:casimir&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt;  
―Hendrik Casimir, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/haphazardreality0000hend/page/296/mode/2up&quot;&gt; &lt;nobr&gt; &lt;i&gt; Haphazard Reality &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在波士顿的生活与社交也为我的观察提供了不少数据点。与我之前读书的纽黑文 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(New Haven)&lt;/span&gt;——一座学术文化相对传统的大学城相比，波士顿有着明显更快的精神节奏与更大的竞争压力——每年成千上万的学生、学者怀着用知识改变命运、改造世界的理想拥入这座美国高等教育和科研资源最集中的城市，投身于科技创新与知识经济的第一线；这里随处可以见到对学术与产业前沿了如指掌、侃侃而谈的青年才俊，而大家的谈话摘要大都围绕若干关键词：人工智能、基因编辑、癌症治疗、药物递送、机器人、量子计算 &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; 无一例外，它们同时也是时下科技资本最关注的话题。在这样的环境中，科研课题若不能引领、追随学术热点或者快速吸引商业资源，就很容易被同行的成果与新闻浪潮淹没甚至淘汰。我在波士顿有幸遇见了不少学业、事业有成并乐在其中的同龄人，但是更常感受的情绪却是疲惫、压抑、焦虑、迷茫。波士顿仿佛正在跑步进入一种学术与科技意义上的新版「摩登时代」——人类创造出的最高效的知识生产流水线要求每个人必须加速思考与劳作，不得犹豫，无暇停歇。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这是科研必然的发展趋势吗？我不知道，但「波士顿模式」的确是当代世界各地的高科技中心争相学习的范本。这是我向往的学术生涯吗？好像是，又好像不是——诚然，热爱探索的人一般都难以拒绝在实力最强的研究机构引领知识潮流的兴奋体验；可是我从中很难感受到一种力量——那种&lt;strong&gt;超出理性、能让人愿意为一份事业不计回报地投入&lt;/strong&gt;的特别力量。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这种力量究竟是什么？我一时无法解答，直到一次旅行中一个偶然的晚上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 五 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;2023&lt;/span&gt; 年夏末，我由芝加哥休假返回波士顿前，在俄亥俄 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(Ohio)&lt;/span&gt; 与肯塔基 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(Kentucky)&lt;/span&gt; 两州的交界城市辛辛那提 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(Cincinnati)&lt;/span&gt; 短作停留。晚饭之后想买一个忘在家中的相机小配件，被谷歌错误地导引到了辛辛那提大学 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(University of Cincinnati)&lt;/span&gt; 旁边的 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Target&lt;/span&gt; 超市。在此之前，我除了听说过它附属的音乐学院 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;College-Conservatory of Music&lt;/span&gt; 外，对辛辛那提大学几乎一无所知。既已来此，何不去去校园走走，也享受一下一周以来难得的一个凉爽夏夜。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;行至物理楼前，随手一搜发现这里竟是美国阿巴拉契亚山脉 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(Appalachian Mountains)&lt;/span&gt; 以西最早授发博士学位的物理系。于是我随兴戴上耳机，在校园里边散步边听 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Aaron Copland&lt;/span&gt; 为 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Martha Graham&lt;/span&gt; 创作的芭蕾音乐 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Appalachian Spring&lt;/span&gt;——&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tsux27kMwjc&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_nwtD--uhyU52oulPKfjOKKmDVD530LfC8&amp;amp;index=1&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/mtt-copland-appalachian.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;首演于 &lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;1944&lt;/span&gt; 年的 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nM5-CsI713g&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Appalachian Spring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 是一部民族主义风格的现代芭蕾，用简约的编舞、布景与配乐描绘了十九世纪初美国西部边境一对新人的成婚。其中最为人熟知音乐片段是由间奏 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(interlude)&lt;/span&gt; 开始的主题—变奏 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(theme and variations)&lt;/span&gt; 段落，其主题旋律引用自十九世纪美国基督教震教派 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(Shakers)&lt;/span&gt; 的歌谣 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ccHfDX9GChc&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_njqc-matMrey91PLHScbAOkh_NGsaKMtg&amp;amp;index=6&quot;&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;“Simple Gifts”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;（后来也被 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Copland&lt;/span&gt; 收入 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7MLjNcpJ4_I&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_nZm6ZjAt3-Xd7vQtFYTKJEXwYizp5c9h4&amp;amp;index=15&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;Old American Songs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 的第一辑中）&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.5em&quot;&gt;：&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
’Tis the gift to be simple, ’tis the gift to be free &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
’Tis the gift to come down where we ought to be &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-ns&quot;&gt;
And when we find ourselves in the place just right &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;poem-last&quot;&gt;
’Twill be in the valley of love and delight &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;那天，我在辛辛那提大学徘徊到接近凌晨才离开。回到民宿后，迅速打开电脑，开始整理自己当前的科研兴趣并查阅有可能匹配的实验室信息。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我准备回学术界了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 六 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Glenn Gould&lt;/span&gt; 于 &lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;1967&lt;/span&gt; 年创作的广播纪录片 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Idea of North&lt;/span&gt;——&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tsux27kMwjc&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_nwtD--uhyU52oulPKfjOKKmDVD530LfC8&amp;amp;index=1&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/gould-solitude.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 参照巴洛克复调音乐的对位 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(counterpoint)&lt;/span&gt; 结构，为 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Idea of North&lt;/span&gt; 设置六个独立「声部」&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;：&lt;/span&gt;四位受访者口述各自因科研、医护、政府工作前往加拿大北方的经历、一位 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 在北方列车上偶遇的退休测绘员的旁白讲述&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:maclean&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:maclean&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;；另外，背景中有节奏的火车轮轨声作为贯穿全片的通奏低音 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(basso continuo)&lt;/span&gt; 。以上音轨经过复杂的后期剪接叠加，纪实与虚构&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;在 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Idea of North&lt;/span&gt; 之后，&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 又完成了两部风格高度类似的续作——&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bg3zolRi5wA&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_nwtD--uhyU52oulPKfjOKKmDVD530LfC8&amp;amp;index=2&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Latecomers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;(1969)&lt;/span&gt; 和 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2v2uiNiubNE&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_nwtD--uhyU52oulPKfjOKKmDVD530LfC8&amp;amp;index=3&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Quiet in the Land&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;num&quot;&gt;(1977)&lt;/span&gt;，主题依然是加拿大北方的环境与人。一个很自然的疑问是：身为古典音乐家的 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 为何会对这一主题如此着迷，以至于十年间用三部跨出本行的严肃作品对其反复挖掘？真正的答案无人知晓，不过我们可以从 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Idea of North&lt;/span&gt; 的专辑注释 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(liner notes)&lt;/span&gt; 中得到一点隐晦提示：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
In one sense, I suppose the train’s basso-continuo is simply an excuse—a foundation for the vocal textures we wanted to concoct above it. But then, “The Idea of North” is itself an excuse—an opportunity to examine that condition of solitude which is neither exclusive to the north nor the prerogative of those who go north but which does, perhaps, appear, with all its ramifications, a bit more clearly to those who have made, if only in their imagination, the journey north. &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p align=&quot;right&quot; class=&quot;quote-ttl&quot;&gt;  
―Glenn Gould, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/cd_solitude-trilogy-three-sound-documentaries_glenn-gould/page/n4/mode/1up&quot;&gt; &lt;nobr&gt;“‘The Idea of North’: An Introduction”&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我认为比较恰当的理解是：&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 纪录片中的「北方」可以引申为一类意象——它指代着现实或精神世界里人迹罕至的僻远境地；每个人在生命中都可以有自己曾经或未曾前往的「北方」&lt;span style=&quot;margin-left:-0.33em&quot;&gt;，&lt;/span&gt;但「北方之旅」首先需要面对远离人群的孤独。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;play&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom:1.0em&quot;&gt;
W.V. MACLEAN.&amp;nbsp; He’s sitting there sort of away from the madding crowd that’s stampeding up and down the aisle. And actually he’s trying to sort of isolate himself because in fact, shortly he will be isolated for a long period of time in the lonely north. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p class=&quot;play&quot;&gt;
W.V. MACLEAN.&amp;nbsp; The person that makes the trip more often, of course, is going to realize that before long, he’s going to be up against himself. Not against his fellow travelers, no, not so much, but he’s going to have to be up against his own sad self.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;比如，我们学生时代一度对科研近乎无限的热情，究竟有多少能转化为日后坚持学术事业的笃定？又有多少是源于无知的「浪漫」情怀？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;play&quot;&gt;
MARIANNE SCHROEDER.&amp;nbsp; It did seem like a very romantic place to me. And this was one of the reasons why I wanted to go north, because considering a place romantic means that one doesn’t know too much about it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;再比如，我们接受学术训练后对专业群体产生的认同与归属感，是否出于真正的志趣相投？亦或只是不愿承认狭小封闭的同行圈子只能彼此接纳、互相慰藉而没有其它选择的无奈事实？&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;play&quot;&gt;
FRANK VALLEE.&amp;nbsp; You are excluding the rest of the world that will never understand, and you have made your own world with these other people. And probably what you will never know and nobody else will ever know is whether you are kidding yourself or not—have you really made your peace with these other people, or have you made a peace because the only alternative to the peace is a kind of crack-up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;play&quot;&gt;
W.V. MACLEAN.&amp;nbsp; There’s no moral equivalent, said William James, no moral equivalent of war. That is that there’s nothing like war for providing something for you to be against. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; So I go on to say that the north is the war, that you can afford to be against Monther Nature, if only humans make it possible. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; No longer do humans combine to defy or to measure or to read or to understand or to live with the thing we call Mother Nature. Our number one enemy instead of being Mother Nature is of course human nature. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; So we’re up against this William James. &lt;nobr&gt;. . .&lt;/nobr&gt; I suppose he meant really that not war, the moral equivalent for us is going north. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E0Ytqf2zXWc&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_loP8ByqcmsH-7hLj9q2cXnEcB1Y19gHo4&amp;amp;index=26&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/gould-goldberg81.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;ttl&quot;&gt; 七 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;alb&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=efnCOVda7-o&amp;amp;list=OLAK5uy_n4gCBZiEJ_Jnh5iWM0BbdTP55-Qb1aWtY&amp;amp;index=3&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/albums/bernstein-sibelius5.png&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;时光荏苒，今年已是我大学本科毕业后的第十年。昔日的同窗多数现在已经成家立业，而我还在知识的大海中没完地扑腾，不知几年后的自己又会身在何处、思虑何事。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:science&quot;&gt;
 	 严格地讲，本文及后续博客文章中谈及的「学术」主要指基础自然科学，但其中一部分探讨对其它相关学科也应该有一定借鉴意义。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:science&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:professional&quot;&gt;
 	 在美国的高等教育系统中，商学院、法学院、医学院等职业学院因为拥有独立的营收来源和评价体系，其教职无论在数量还是薪酬待遇上一般都要比自然科学、人文社科等传统学术院系高出很多；面向应用的工程学科大致介于两者之间。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:professional&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:anthropology&quot;&gt;
 	 这些机会与我的另一方面兴趣正好契合：博士期间，我曾在专业之外探索过科学史与科学技术研究 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(science and technology studies)&lt;/span&gt; 的一些当代前沿，其中包括用人类学方法研究科学家群体特征和现代科学实践原则的分支 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(anthropology of science)&lt;/span&gt; 。尽管工业界工作与人类学研究之间的差距不能更大，我还是希望能受益于自己此刻在科研生态系统中的独特位置，收获一些对当前量子物理研究和量子科技产业的新认识——尤其是其作为有组织的人类活动对个体与社会的现实影响。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:anthropology&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:industry&quot;&gt;
 	 截至目前我有且仅有一段工业界经历，因此不能确定自己感受到的这些「优势」哪些在工业界普遍存在，哪些只是因为自己巧合选到了一家好公司。特别提示：上班有风险、入职需谨慎。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:industry&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rent&quot;&gt;
 	 再考虑到波士顿这些年飞涨的房租和物价，工作后实际可支配收入占总收入的比例相比之前没有太大变化。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rent&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mfa&quot;&gt;
 	 比如波士顿美术馆 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(Museum of Fine Arts)&lt;/span&gt; 每周四与周五晚上会延长开馆至十点，人流量明显少于周末，这通常是我最喜欢去闲逛的时间。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mfa&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:overhead&quot;&gt;
 	 在美国的研究型大学，科研团队获得外部资助后需要按比例将其中一部分（平均可以达到 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;40%&lt;/span&gt; 甚至更高）作为间接支出 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;(indirect/overhead cost)&lt;/span&gt; 上交给学校。这笔「管理费」通常显著高于学校为科研活动提供行政与基础设施支持的成本，其多余部分会被用于学校的建设扩张、院系之间的「转移支付」等与科研本身并无直接关联的项目，是学校可支配营收的重要组成。现实中，征收间接支出已经成为许多资源有限、预算紧张的大学开展科研活动最直接的动机。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:overhead&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:casimir&quot;&gt;
 	 这段话在书中是被 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Casimir&lt;/span&gt; 作为对立观点引用；他自己对此并不完全赞同，认为这种观点高估了大公司的决策能力，并低估了学术工作者的独立性。作为理论物理学家的 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Casimir&lt;/span&gt; 二战后长期领导飞利浦公司下属的物理实验室 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Philips Natuurkundig Laboratorium&lt;/span&gt;，他对技术和商业之于当代科学的影响总体持积极态度。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:casimir&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:maclean&quot;&gt;
 	 这位 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;W.V. “Wally” Maclean&lt;/span&gt; 是 &lt;span class=&quot;ita&quot;&gt;The Idea of North&lt;/span&gt; 中的一个神秘角色：相比于其他四位能够通过署名出版物或追踪采访记录确认身份的受访者，&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Wally&lt;/span&gt; 的背景仅仅在纪录片引言中被 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 简单提及，于公开网域再无任何信息；另外，&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Wally&lt;/span&gt; 偏向书面化、台词化的讲述风格与其余四人差异明显，反而很接近 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 自己独特的语言习惯。尽管没有更多证据，我个人仍然倾向于猜测 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Wally&lt;/span&gt; 即使在现实中确有其人，他在片中的「声部」主要也是 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 的重新创作；&lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Wally&lt;/span&gt; 关于北方的理解正是 &lt;span class=&quot;reg&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/span&gt; 自己对孤独意义的感悟。
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:maclean&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
